A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Ann C. Whitman - Politics, Series P FA351
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Ann C. Whitman - Politics, Series P
1958-1973
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Whitman, Ann
FA351
25 document box(es)
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller was born on July 8, 1908, in Bar Harbor, Maine, the third child of John Davison Rockefeller, Jr., and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. He graduated from the Lincoln School of Teachers College at Columbia University in New York City in 1926. Mr. Rockefeller attended Dartmouth College where he was elected to Phi Beta Kappa, graduating cum laude in 1930 with an A.B. degree in economics.
After college, Mr. Rockefeller was active in family enterprises, including real estate, banking, and family philanthropies. His major business interests in time became focused on Rockefeller Center and Latin America. In 1938, he became the president of Rockefeller Center.
In 1935, because of his interest in national affairs and his desire to learn about U.S. business abroad, Mr. Rockefeller became a director of Creole Petroleum Company, the Venezuelan subsidiary of Standard Oil of New Jersey. This association led eventually to his deep, life-long interest in Latin America. He made extensive visits to Latin America in 1937 and 1939 to study economic, social, and political conditions. He resigned his directorship in the Creole Petroleum Company in 1940.
In 1940, Mr. Rockefeller and his four brothers organized the Rockefeller Brothers Fund to carry out a broad range of philanthropic activities.
Throughout his life Mr. Rockefeller was an avid supporter of the arts. He served as a trustee, treasurer, president, and chair of the board of the Museum of Modern Art, which was cofounded by his mother. In 1954, he founded the Museum of Primitive Art, which collected of indigenous art of the Americas, Africa, Oceania, and early Asia and Europe.
After his 1939 visit to Latin America, Mr. Rockefeller prepared a memorandum for President Franklin D. Roosevelt outlining his deep concern over Nazi influence and penetration into that part of the world. In the memo he recommended a U.S. program of cooperation with the nations of the western hemisphere to achieve better relations among these nations and to help raise their standards of living. Largely as a result of this memo, President Roosevelt asked Mr. Rockefeller in August of 1940 to initiate and head a new program ultimately known as the Office of Inter-American Affairs. Mr. Rockefeller served as Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, his first full-time position in public service.
Mr. Rockefeller served in this position until December 1944, when President Roosevelt appointed him Assistant Secretary of State for American Republic Affairs. In this post, Mr. Rockefeller initiated the Inter-American Conference on Problems of War and Peace in Mexico City in February of 1945. It resulted in the Act of Chapultepec, which provided the framework for economic, social, and defense cooperation among the nations of the western hemisphere and set the principle that an attack on one of these nations would be regarded as an attack on all and jointly resisted.
Mr. Rockefeller signed the Act of Chapultepec on behalf of the United States. He also attended the United Nations Conference on International Organization in San Francisco in 1945. At the conference, there was considerable opposition to the idea of permitting, within the UN Charter, the formation of regional pacts such as the Act of Chapultepec. Mr. Rockefeller, who believed that the inclusion was essential, especially to U.S. policy in Latin America, successfully argued the need for regional pacts within the framework of the United Nations. The importance of this victory was underscored by the subsequent formation of NATO, SEATO, and the Rio Pact.
During these war-time years, Mr. Rockefeller also served as Chairman of the Inter-American Development Commission, which was established in June 1940 to reorganize and revitalize Latin American economies following the loss of European markets. He was also the U.S. Co-Chairman of the Mexican-American Development Commission to help Mexico emerge as an industrial nation in the transition from war to peace.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Assistant Secretary of State on August 24, 1945.
Upon his return to private life in New York in 1946, Mr. Rockefeller became chair of the board of Rockefeller Center and undertook a program of physical expansion. Two other initiatives during this period illustrate Mr. Rockefeller's continuing interest in Latin America and international economic development. In July of 1946, the Rockefeller brothers established a philanthropic organization, the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA). AIA financed nonprofit projects to ameliorate health, educational, agricultural, and other social problems in the poorer areas of Latin America. Nelson Rockefeller served as President from July 1946 to June 1953 and from January 1957 to December 1958. In 1947, he organized the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC), a business corporation to help raise living standards in foreign countries through new economic enterprises. In its early years, IBEC concentrated on enterprises in Latin America but later expanded its activities to other regions. Mr. Rockefeller served as IBEC President from January 1947 to June 1953 and from January 1956 to December 1958.
In his inaugural address in January 1949, President Harry S. Truman announced the Point IV program for providing technical assistance to developing nations. This concept was based in part on programs Mr. Rockefeller and his associates had developed through the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs and the private, philanthropic AIA. In November of 1950, President Truman asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the International Development Advisory Board. The Board was charged with recommending policies for carrying out the Point IV program. The Board's report, entitled "Partners in Progress," provided the basic blueprint for America's foreign assistance program.
On November 20, 1952, President-elect Dwight D. Eisenhower asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization, a group created to recommend ways to improve the efficiency of the executive branch of the government. As Chairman of that committee, Mr. Rockefeller recommended 13 reorganization plans to the President, 10 of which were approved by Congress. These plans achieved basic changes in the organization of the Department of Defense, the Department of Agriculture, and the Office of Defense Mobilization, among others. Another of the plans led to the establishment of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. In June 1953, Mr. Rockefeller was appointed Under Secretary of the new department. He was especially active in the department's legislative program, recommending measures that covered an additional ten million people under the Social Security program. He resigned as HEW Under Secretary in 1954 to become Special Assistant to the President for Foreign Affairs.
While serving as Special Assistant, Mr. Rockefeller played a key role in the development of the "Open Skies" proposal for checking on world armaments through mutual air reconnaissance. He accompanied President Eisenhower to the Geneva Summit Conference in 1955, where the plan was proposed to the world by the President. Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Special Assistant on December 31, 1955.
Mr. Rockefeller first ran for public office in 1958 and was elected Governor of New York on November 4, defeating incumbent Averill Harriman. He took office January 1, 1959, and was subsequently re-elected Governor three more times, thus becoming the first Governor in the nation's history to be elected to four 4-year terms.
Nelson Rockefeller's tenure as a public servant in the federal government was a formative period in his life. By the time he left Washington to assume the governorship of New York, he had received a thorough education in the workings of the federal government. His chairmanship of PACGO permitted him to examine every aspect of the executive branch. This and his work in HEW exposed him to a wide variety of domestic issues. He gained experience in initiating legislation, in foreign policy and diplomacy, in domestic and international economics, and in national security and military affairs. In the process he also received an education in national politics and gained a reputation for being an effective and hardworking administrator. Most importantly, these appointments provided him with the opportunity to form the friendships and personal associations that served him throughout his political career.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Governor of New York in December 1973. In August 1974, President Gerald R. Ford nominated him to fill the vacant vice presidency following the resignation of President Richard M. Nixon. Mr. Rockefeller served as Vice President from December 19, 1974, to January 20, 1977. Nelson Rockefeller died on January 26, 1979, in New York City.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 04 P
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The series is arranged primarily alphabetically by correspondent. Each letter of the alphabet begins with general correspondence files and then follows with individual folders for specific correspondents. It is not clear why some people received separate folders (often a folder contains only a single piece of correspondence) while others were maintained in the general file.
Biographical/Historical note
Ann Cook Whitman was born in Perry, Ohio, in 1908. She attended Antioch College, where she enrolled in the school's work-study program. The program sent her to the Institute for Child Guidance in New York. Becoming a secretary, she left college. Her next job was as a personal secretary to Adele Rosenwald Levy, whose father was a founder of Sears, Roebuck and Company.
In the 1950s, Whitman worked for the Committee for a Free Europe. She was recruited to work for the Dwight D. Eisenhower presidential campaign in 1952, going on to serve as personal secretary to President Eisenhower throughout his eight years in the White House and for a short time at his retirement home, Gettysburg.
In 1961, she began working for George Hinman, a political advisor to Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller. In 1965, she became Governor Rockefeller's executive assistant, and she later served as Rockefeller's chief of staff during his Vice Presidential tenure. Whitman then returned to New York, assisting Rockefeller until her retirement in 1977. She died in 1991.
Scope and Contents note
This series contains a portion of Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller's political correspondence on state and national issues. The correspondence reflects his role as a national political figure and was filed separately from correspondence generated while serving as Governor of New York.
Many incoming letters bear Governor Rockefeller's handwritten notations indicating the response he wished drafted (e.g., "note of thanks," or "ack" for acknowledgment). Mrs. Whitman would distribute letters to the staff for response, and she also responded to letters on her own.
Some incoming letters included attachments, primarily newspaper clippings and photographs. Most of the photographs are of Governor Rockefeller at public events. In some cases, the photos were taken by professional photographers, although the majority are personal snapshots.
There are several files of miscellaneous material at the end of the series. Included among them are four folders of "Impeachment Letters, October to November 1973" (Box 23, Folders 530-533). These letters are from the general public urging Governor Rockefeller to speak out about the Constitutional crisis caused by the growing Watergate debacle. A majority of the letters asks Governor Rockefeller to use his influence either to convince President Nixon that he should resign or to convince Congress to impeach the President. Another file, entitled "Drug Abuse Program" (Box 23, Folder 528), contains information on the genesis of the Rockefeller drug laws of 1973. Box 25 contains four oversized items removed from other portions of the series.
This series contains the office files of Ann C. Whitman. They document official activities in the execution of her duties as members of Rockefeller's staff. The actions, decisions, and exchanges of information or points of view documented here occurred in the course of proposing and implementing policies for the Rockefeller administration, political campaigns, and/or Rockefeller's personal activities. However, unless a document is personally signed by Nelson A. Rockefeller, or is referred to in a document personally signed by him, it should not be assumed he saw the document or was aware of its existence or substance. Furthermore, researchers should bear in mind that staff files may contain documents or drafts addressed to Rockefeller which were never shown to him.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller papers, Activities (FA338)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, AIA-IBEC (FA339)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Art (FA340)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Countries (FA341)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, DNA (FA342)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Family and Friends (FA343)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Oral Histories (FA344)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - New York City Office (FA345)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - George L. Hinman (FA346)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - Oscar M. Ruebhausen (FA347)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Projects (FA348)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Speeches, Post-Vice Presidential (FA349)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Washington, DC (FA350)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Hugh Morrow Interviews (FA352)
New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Political campaigns -- United States; Political science; Public health -- Latin America; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Social problems -- Latin America; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Venezuela; State governments -- United States; United States; Philanthropy -- New York (State); Philanthropy -- United States; Latin America; International relations -- United States; International relations; International economic relations; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Government policy; Government agencies; Education -- Latin America; Federal government -- United States; Agriculture -- Latin America; Agriculture; Arts; Art, Primitive; Business; Brazil; Civic improvement; Business enterprises, Foreign; Developing countries; Civics; Economics; Economic policy; National security -- United States; Philanthropy; Education
- A General (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Abbot, Jarold: 1970, visit abroad and to the "Ethenos." Abbot, Jere: 1970, art exhibit, Colby College. Abrams, Albert J.: 1971, State Senate "official" golf balls. Adams, Sherman: 1965, appointment. Alacoque, Mary (Sister): 1966, Saint Margaret Mary School, Albany. Set of Audubon Nature Encyclopedias sent. Albert, Daniel G.: 1965, New York State Supreme Court Justice. Requests NAR loan of art to temple. Aldrich, Winthrop: 1972, thank-you letter (NAR's cousin). Allen, Ray: 1972, thanks for Grand Canyon visit. Alsop, Joseph: 1959, press interview. Altschul, Frank: 1967, requests lunch with NAR. "Senior Citizen of 1967." Amper, Gay: 1960, thanks to NAR for condolences. Annenberg, Walter (Mr. & Mrs.): 1968-1971, U.S. Ambassador to Britain. NAR's trips to London, California. Thanks. Apple, R.W., Jr.: 1966-1968, returning to U.S. from Vietnam. "New York Times" correspondent. Armour, Claude A.: 1973-1974, providing security at Republican Governors Conference, Memphis, Tennessee. Arruda, Ivo: 1968, supports NAR presidential bid, reply from Berent Friele. Ascoli, Max: 1967, invitation from NAR to Arden House Conference for 100th Anniversary of New York State Board of Social Welfare. Askew, Edward (Mrs.): 1973, thank you for dinner in Des Moines & photos. Astor, Brooke: 1968-1971, postcard. Chair for Monroe Wheeler. Aumont, Jean Pierre: 1964, thanks for interest in presidential bid. Avnet, Lester: 1968, $25,000 Science Scholarship at Yeshiva University.
- Adinolfi, Anthony G. (Mrs.), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Condolences on the death of her husband, completion of South Mall Project.
- Adler, Louis C., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Congratulations on appointment as Director of News Operations for WCBS. Apologies for embarrassing questions at interview.
- Agnew, Spiro T., 1967-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Borrowing TV commercial. Sends speech material. Top positions in new administration, request for recommendations. $15 million grant from the Ford Foundation to the Fund for the Republic. Memo from C.D. Ward with a letter from Agnew to Speaker of House Carl Albert re: inquiry into charges against Agnew.
- Albano, Vincent F., Jr., 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Thank you. Recommendation for Irving Kirschenbaum. Century National Bank. Congratulations.
- Albright, Harry W., Jr., 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Liaison to Scott Commission. Commission on the Quality, Cost & Financing of New York State Primary and Secondary Education. Memo of events from October 1969. Appointments to vacancies and promotions.
- Aldrich, Alexander, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Invitation to NAR to join the Board of Negro Heritage. Hudson River Valley Commission (HRVC). Trip to Storm King Mountain. Federal Compact Proposal for Hudson River Valley Commission.
- Aldrich, Richard S., 1966-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Attorney Room 5400. First Washington Securities merger. Reapportionment case.
- Aldrich, Richard S., Jr., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Thank you for wedding gift.
- Alfange, Dean, 1967-1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Thank you for "A Middle East Dialogue." Memo on inflation; memo and telegram concerning a situation in Greece. Racing problems. Resignation of Carl Spad. Vietnam.
- Ammidon, Hoyt, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Comments on bill to amend abandoned property law; list of programs in the Executive Budget for reduction.
- Anderson, Robert B., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Letter of introduction and resume on Edward J. Heine, Jr.
- Anderson, Warren, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Congratulations. Reservations for Caneel Bay for Wendell Miller. Actions taken re: procedures for legislative session. Budget briefings under review. Mass Transit Bond Issue Bill. Sale of portion of property near Creedmoor. Plans to be out of country.
- Andrade, Victor, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Spanish-American voters. Congratulations on outstanding job as Organization of American States representative. Copies of report on the Orinoco, Cassiquiare, Negro Waterway.
- Annigoni, Pietro, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Visit to studio.
- Antinori, Piero, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Thanks for visit while in Italy.
- Aragon, Louis R., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Re: Rockefeller Foundation.
- Armstrong, Anne (Mrs. Tobin), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Thank you. Recommendations for National Commission on the Future of America in its Third Century.
- Armstrong, Tobin, 1965-1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Report on a trip to South America. Condolence speech at Memorial Service for Winthrop Rockefeller.
- Arpels, Claude, 1966-1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Sends computer wrist watch. Thank you for gift of jeweled elephant.
- Ash, Roy L., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Sends application to United States Information Agency.
- Atherton, Flo Kampmann (Mrs. Holt), no date (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Visit with NAR, comments on Commission on Critical Choices, campaign & election day.
- Atkins, Ollie, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Thanks for photos with the President.
- Augay, Peter, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Thank you.
- Axtel, Ned, Jr., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  NAR sent check for $100 to defray expenses with Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board.
- B General (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Bachrach, Fabian: 1966, complimentary print of NAR's portrait. Backus, Dana Converse (Mrs.): 1970, invitation to Rockefeller Brothers for United Nations Association of New York, 25th Anniversary Dinner. Bader, William B.: 1967, thanks and copy of resume. Baker, George E.: 1966, Latin America, pages missing. Balanchine, George: 1965, New York State Arts Council, letter from NAR. Ballien, Gloria M.: 1973, attorney on South Mall Committee. Letter regarding service on Committee. List of South Mall Committee members. Memo from T.N. Hurd re: South Mall Committee. Barr, Alfred H., Jr. (Mr. & Mrs.): 1961-1972, thanks for Christmas gifts & cards. Barr, Donald: 1969, letter to the Headmaster of the Dalton School re: the admission of Edward Logue's children to Dalton. de Barros, Adhemar: 1963, letter from Berent Friele re: loan application to Inter-American Development Bank. Bartol, Blair (Miss): 1966, invitation to speak at Wheelock College. Bartol, George E. (Mrs.): 1970-1971, thanks for Christmas gifts. Bassinger, Carl O. (Reverend): 1968, supports NAR for President. Alleges King assassination conspiracy. Bass, Robert: 1959, Letter to George Hinman suggesting NAR letters to New Hampshire politicians. Beach, Tad: no date, invitation to dinner party. Beer, Meme Houghton: no date, thanks for wedding gift. Bennett, Pauline: 1965, NAR thanks for birthday wishes. Berentson, Buehl: 1969, Executive Director of the Republican Governors Association, list of committees. Berle, Adolph: 1968-1970, NAR thanks for letter, congratulations on NAR Latin American Report. NAR talking with Dick Goodwin at White House. Letter to NAR re: Dr. Serrato and son-in-law. Invites NAR to dinner, acknowledment and acceptance of invitation. Berthier, Anice: 1961, list of doctors Laurance Spelman Rockefeller saw in Albany. Bigart, Homer: 1969, condolences. Blackburn, Ben (The Hon.): 1973, thanks for introduction to the Southern Republican Conference. Blakely, Ann (Mrs.): 1966, NAR thanks for gift. Blakeman, R. S. (Mrs.): 1959, NAR thanks for comments on his Inaugural Speech. Bliss, Ray: 1965, Republican Coordinating Committee Meeting. Bliss, Robert: 1967, clipping for NAR. Bogdan, Norbert A.: 1959, President, American Overseas Finance Committee. Bohlen, Charles A.: 1966, Ambassador to France. Visit.
- B General (Box 1, Folder 27)